"Is Shrimp Good for You?
Antibiotic Resistance"
About 90% of shrimp
consumed in the United States
is imported,
and because much
imported seafood
is farm-raised
in confined conditions,
drugs are used to prevent
or treat disease
and increase survival rates,
and residues
of some of these drugs
can cause cancer
or allergic reactions
or contribute
to antibiotic resistance.
Among different kinds
of seafood,
shrimp have had
the highest frequency
of veterinary drug violations,
primarily for nitrofurans
and chloramphenicol.
The United States banned
chloramphenicol 35 years ago
due to a link with
a rare and often fatal disease
called aplastic anemia.
Nitrofurans are also dangerous
because of their potential
cancer-causing properties.
So, their use in animals
produced for human consumption
is similarly banned
in Europe and the United States.
For something as potentially
dangerous as chloramphenicol,
governments around the world
have established
zero-tolerance policies,
which means that no residues
in food are permissible.
However,
traces of chloramphenicol
have been detected in shrimp.
Unlike most of the animals
we eat,
who have multiple organs
for drug excretion,
shrimp possess only one,
which may allow more antibiotics
to build up in them.
But you don't know
until you put it to the test.
There have been
four studies published
on the presence of banned drugs
in retail U.S. shrimp.
One found that 92% of imported,
farm-raised shrimp
tested positive
for at least one drug
that is banned for use
in the United States.
Another, of just
six shrimp from stores
in Arizona and California,
found drugs in two of them.
The third tested dozens
purchased in Louisiana
from many
of our main shrimp importers,
and 70% tested positive
for the zero-tolerance
carcinogenic nitrofurantoin.
Of all the countries,
Vietnam appeared
to be sending us shrimp
with the most types
of antibiotic residues.
The 100% positives
in Bangladesh and Ecuador
were based on just
a single positive sample--
one out of one--
for both countries.
The fourth, however,
found no antibiotic residues.
Unfortunately,
only a small fraction of imports
are tested by the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration,
and, therefore,
the potential for shipments
with antibiotic tainted shrimp
to slip through the cracks
remains.
And they're mostly from Asia,
which has been identified as
posing a very significant risk
to the global burden
of antibiotic resistance.
Stocking densities on shrimp
farms are often very high,
which concentrates bacteria
and raises stress levels
in the animals,
which increases their
susceptibility to infection,
leading to outbreaks
that kill, like,
a billion shrimp at a time.
Shrimp don't respond
to vaccination;
so, to combat disease,
farmers employ
a range of chemicals,
the residues of which can end up
in the final product we may eat.
Even in more
traditional systems,
where human and animal waste
is dumped into shrimp ponds,
the antibiotics
that end up in the manure
end up just increasing
overall antibiotic exposure.
Aside from the potential for
fostering antibiotic resistance,
consuming antibiotic residues
can have a direct toxic effect,
and the constant traces
of antibiotics
can also disrupt
the human microbiome,
as has been demonstrated.
The consumption
of shrimp containing
potentially unsafe levels
of antibiotics from aquaculture,
shrimp farming,
is a global concern
due to overuse of antibiotics.
There is clearly an urgent need
for governments to regulate
the use of antibiotics
in crustacean production.
In 2001,
chloramphenicol was detected
in shrimp imported
into Europe from Asia,
triggering a food scandal,
and the regulatory response
spilled over
to other major
seafood-importing countries,
including the United States.
The U.S.
Food and Drug Administration
started testing and every year
has rejected shrimp
due to the presence
of antimicrobial drugs,
the most contaminated
of all tested seafood products.
That shows the system
is working, right?
Well, only a small amount
of imported seafood
is actually inspected.
How small?
For shrimp, about four samples
out of every 10 million pounds
(4,535 tons)
of shrimp are tested.
So, assuming there are about
25 shrimp in a pound (0.45 kg),
that's like one sample tested
for every 60 million shrimp.
Of course,
they come in big batches,
yet the FDA only tests
about 0.1%
of the million annual shipments
that come in every year.
Based on this level of testing,
seafood shipments from
a foreign processing facility
would have a roughly
one-in-a-thousand chance
of being selected by the FDA
for drug residue testing.
Is that because positive
findings are so rare? No.
About every one in every 10
shipments of shrimp tested
turns up contaminated
with unsafe drug residues.
So, that means
like a hundred shipments
of the other 999
that weren't tested
may also be contaminated;
yet, they can go straight to
restaurants or grocery stores.
And we only test
for a few drugs.
Europe, Japan, and Canada
are picking up
seven to 10 different drugs,
whereas we only look for two.
So, we are likely missing
the wider range of drugs
picked up by other countries.
Why doesn't the FDA test more?
According to FDA officials,
they don't have the resources
to test more.
Okay, said the GAO,
which is
the congressional watchdog,
how about forcing the countries
that are sending the shrimp
to test for drugs
before they ship them here?
Let them pay for it.
That's what Europe does.
Well, the FDA decided
not to pursue such agreements
with other countries
to require them to test seafood
exported to the United States
for unsafe drug residues,
as Europe does.
Why not?
They didn't think some of the
countries that send us shrimp
might be able to,
because they lack
the laboratory infrastructure
and capabilities needed
to test for the drugs
of concern to the FDA.
I'm reminded of an outbreak
investigation of salmonella
linked to shrimp,
where the investigators had
to explain to the exporters
that they probably shouldn't be
scooping up shrimp
off the floor.
But wait, countries exporting
to Europe are able to comply;
so, what ends up happening
is that the United States
may still be a market
for at least some seafood
that did not meet
the safety standards of Europe.
As a result, shrimp that cannot
be shipped to European countries
because of concerns
about violative drug residues
may be shipped to
the United States, no problem.
It's like the use
of some coloring agents
used to disguise
shrimp diseases:
approved in the United States
but prohibited elsewhere
due to concerns about causing
ADHD symptoms in children.
Countries know they can
always send products here,
and even if they do use drugs
they aren't supposed to,
there's only a one-in-a-thousand
chance we'll even check.